Finding Aid for the Albert and Charles Boni, Inc. records, ca. 1916-1974 LSC.1462
UCLA Library Special Collections
Albert and Charles Boni, Inc. records
ca. 1916-1974
UCLA Library Special Collections
Albert & Charles Boni
LSC.1462
5 Linear Feet 10 boxes
Albert Boni (1892-1981) founded Albert and Charles Boni, Incorporated with his brother in New York City (1923). They introduced Boni Paper Books, and sold them by mail-order subscription. Active in both literary and political fields, the firm published such controversial and influential writers as Marcel Proust, Colette, D.H. Lawrence, Upton Sinclair and Leon Trotsky. The collection consists of papers relating to Albert and Charles Boni, Incorporated.
no content
Restrictions on Access
Stored off-site. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Boni, 1985.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942303043606533
Biography/History
Albert Boni was born in 1892 in New York City and attended Harvard University. Between the two World Wars Albert Boni left a lasting impression on the publishing world, first with Horace Liveright (Boni & Liveright) and then with his brother Charles (Albert & Charles Boni, Inc.). Boni's first publishing venture was The Little Leather Library, which sold abridged classics in a very small format through Woolworth's (1914). After selling the Washington Square Bookshop in 1917, he joined Horace Liveright to form the Boni-Liveright Publishing Company, which started the Modern Library of the World's Best Classics. Modern Library intended to copy the success of the popular British Everyman Series; in 1925, Boni's salesman Bennett Cerf bought the line, and went on to start Random House. With Albert and Charles Boni, Inc., he moved away from repackaging the classics in hopes of publishing exciting contemporary literature. By 1923 Boni and his brother founded Albert and Charles Boni, Incorporated, a firm that introduced Boni Paper Books and sold them by mail-order subscription. Active in both the literary and the political fields, the firm published such controversial and influential writers as Marcel Proust, Colette, D.H. Lawrence, Upton Sinclair, and Leon Trotsky. In the 1940s, Boni's interest in photography and light technologies led him to create the Readex Microprint Corporation. He died on July 13, 1981 in Ormond Beach, Florida.
Scope and Content
The bulk of this collection records Boni's commercial concerns as a publisher; his social and literary interests are clear through correspondence with a variety of artists and writers, from Max Eastman and George Bernard Shaw to Jim Tully. The collection also includes papers related to the Readex Microprint Corporation and Boni's photography compilation, A guide to the literature of photography and related subjects.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Miscellaneous business papers, 1928-1974 (Boxes 1-2).
Correspondence, 1916-1966 (Boxes 3-5).
Contracts, 1921-1973 (Boxes 5-10).
Related Material
Albert Boni Collection of Material about Photography (Collection 1046). Available at UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections.
Publishers and publishing -- United States -- Archives.; Albert & Charles Boni--Archives.; Boni, Albert; Boni, Charles
- Series 1: Miscellaneous Business Papers,., 1928-1974; (2 boxes).
  Scope and Contents note
  Assorted business files.
  - Articles and Inquiries., 1924-1928.; (11 items). (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Papers on The American Library, Melville, Mexico.
  - Business Documents., 1936-1948.; (19 items). (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Invoices, letters.
    1 legal file on Boni vs. R.H. Macy & Company.
  - Business Letters., 1926-1933.; (77 items). (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Letters regarding Albert Boni's various publishing interests, including Creative Arts.
  - Checks Received., 1950 March 9.; (2 items). (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Check stubs for Devil's Dictionary and World's Best Poems.
  - Copyright Inquiries., 1947-1949.; (6 items). (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Inquiries into Boni copyrights.
  - Disputed Contracts., 1929-1930.; (10 items). (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Disputed contracts and financial records of A & C Boni, Inc.
  - Photography Correspondence., 1943-1945.; (58 items). (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Letters and papers concerning Albert Boni's Index to the Literature of Photography.
  - Photography Papers., 1943-1947.; (15 items). (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Letters and papers on photography.
    Article on work of Therese Bonney.
  - Private Bills., 1950-1951.; (72 items). (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Receipts from Albert Boni's life in Chester, Vermont.
  - Publishing Inquiries., 1936-1947.; (48 items). (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Business papers and letters.
  - Readex Corporation., 1949-1951.; (57 items). (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Personal and business letters.
  - Royal Photographic Society., 1950.; (3 items). (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Membership documents.
  - Thornton Wilder Financials., 1950-1974.; (159 items). (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
    International royalty statements for Wilder.
  - Thornton Wilder Translations., 1928-1934.; (76 items). (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
    Letters seeking rights to translate The Bridge of Saint Luis Rey.
  - Titles., n.d.; (4 items). (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Typed lists of A & C Boni titles.
    Handwritten emendations.
    A separate list for Charles Boni Titles.
  - Unsolicited Manuscripts., 1945-1947.; (20 items). (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Cover letters for various unsolicited manuscripts.
- Series 2: Correspondence,., 1916-1966; (3 boxes).
  Assorted correspondence with various authors. Arranged alphabetically by correspondent's surname.
  - Archibald, Norman., 1936 June 15.; (1 item). (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Typewritten letter from Archibald concerning royalties.
  - Beardsley, Aubrey., n.d.; (1 item). (Box 3, Folder 2)
    General note
    See Box 4, Folder 1 for (slightly oversize) original signed proof: "How King Arthur Saw the Questing Beast and Thereof Had Great Marvel," 1893.
  - Bierce, Ambrose., 1937-1947.; (16 items). (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Inquiries into the publishing rights of Bierce's work.
  - Bonsels, Waldemar., 1927-1930.; (27 items). (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Letters from Bonsels in German about Indian Journey.
    1 postcard.
  - Brandeis, Alice and Judge Louis., 1929-1931.; (8 items). (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Letters from Alice about Karl Goldmark.
    1 postcard photo of Goldmark.
    Letters to Louis on publishing.
  - Britton, Nan., 1932.; (5 items). (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Book order inquiries from Britton.
  - Butts, Mary., 1926-1928.; (20 items). (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Correspondence with Butts on various manuscripts.
  - Chubb, Thomas C., 1931-1933.; (53 items). (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Letters and papers from Chubb on Ships and Lovers and Aretino.
    1 photo of Chubb.
  - Coffin, Robert P.T., 1926-1932.; (12 items). (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Letters from Coffin about Dew and Bronze.
  - Croft, F.W., 1927.; (12 items). (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Publishing records for Croft.
  - Dakers, A.H., 1919-1921.; (24 items). (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Correspondence with the Curtis Brown publishing firm.
  - DeCasseres, Benjamin., 1927-1928.; (5 items). (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Handwritten letters from DeCasseres.
  - Draper, Eben and Hazel., 1935.; (8 items). (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Correspondence with Drapers on PR for Norman Archibald's Heaven High, Hell Deep.
  - Dunn, Robert., 1949-1950.; (12 items). (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Correspondence with Dunn about his manuscript.
  - Eastman, Max., 1927-1930.; (12 items). (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Typewritten manuscripts of poem, "The Songs of Love", and story, "Something French."
    Letters about Marx, Lenin and the Science of Revolution.
  - Eddison, E.R., 1926.; (5 items). (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Letters from Eddison about The Worm Ouroboros.
  - Egerton, [C.?]., 1930.; (8 items). (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Handwritten letters from Egerton.
  - Einstein, Elsa., 1930-1931.; (2 items). (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Personal letters between Einstein and Albert Boni.
  - Eliot, T.S., n.d.; (1 item). (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Photostat of handwritten note from Eliot.
  - Feinberg, Charles., 1947-1950.; (6 items). (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Personal correspondence with Feinberg on book collecting.
  - Ferrero, Guglielmo., 1929-1930.; (10 items). (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Correspondence with Ferrero about Unification of the World.
  - Field, Sara Bard., 1932-1937.; (81 items). (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Correspondence with Field about Barabbas.
  - Flanner, Janet., 1929-1930.; (11 items). (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Letters from Flanner about her translations of Colette.
  - Flores, Angel., 1927-1931.; (9 items). (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Correspondence with Flores on book projects.
  - Ford, Ford Madox., 1926 January 29.; (1 item). (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Typewritten letter from Ford about royalties.
  - Handy, W.C., 1925-1926.; (33 items). (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Correspondence with Handy and E.A. Niles about Blues Anthology.
  - Hamilton, Dr. G.V., 1928-1929.; (4 items). (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Correspondence about A Research in Marriage.
  - Helm, William P., 1932.; (8 items). (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Letters from Helm about Washington Swindle Sheet.
  - Jeffers, Robinson., ca. 1932.; (1 item). (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Typewritten letter from Jeffers to Sara Bard Field.
  - Kayser, Rudolph., 1929-1931.; (7 items). (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Publishing related correspondence.
  - Kent, Rockwell., 1928-1929.; (20 items). (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Correspondence with Kent about Creative Arts
    Galleys of illustrated Bridge of Saint Luis Rey.
  - Kropotkin, Peter., n.d.; (2 items). (Box 3, Folder 32)
    2 photos of Kropotkin.
  - Beardsley, Aubrey., n.d.; (2 items). (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Original signed proof and envelope from Beardsley studio: "How King Arthur Saw the Questing Beast and Thereof Had Great Marvel," 1893.
  - Lavell, Charles., 1926-1938.; (35 items). (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Business correspondence with literary agent.
  - Lewisohn, Ludwig., 1927.; (4 items). (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Letters from Lewisohn about The Case of Mr. Crump.
  - Liggett, Walter., 1931.; (40 items). (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Correspondence with Ligget about The Rise of Herbert Hoover.
  - Liveright, Horace., 1920.; (4 items). (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Letters from Liveright to Nell Boni.
  - Locke, Alain., 1926-1933.; (15 items). (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Correspondence with Locke about The New Negro and Rene Maran's Kongo.
  - Malcolm-Smith, E.F., 1930.; (16 items). (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Correspondence with Malcolm-Smith about her translation of Romain Rolland.
  - Marks, Jeannette., 1928-1929.; (31 items). (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Correspondence with Marks about Thirteen Days.
  - Mathers, E. Powys., 1926 May 1.; (1 item). (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Typewritten letter from Mathers.
  - McAdoo, William., 1931.; (65 items). (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Letters, papers, negotiations for serialization of McAdoo's memoirs.
  - McBride, Henry., 1931 June 22 and n.d.; (2 items). (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Handwritten notes from McBride.
  - McFee, Henry Lee., 1929.; (5 items). (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Correspondence with painter McFee.
  - Miscellany., 1924-1947.; (35 items). (Box 4, Folder 13-15)
    Variety of correspondences with friends, writers, booksellers.
  - Motherwell, Hiram., 1928.; (1 item). (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Correspondence with the translator of Mussolini's The Cardinal's Mistress.
  - Newman, Frances., 1927 December 16.; (1 item). (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Handwritten letter from Newman.
  - Owen, Robert., 1927.; (6 items). (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Correspondence with Owen about The Russian Imperial Conspiracy.
  - Pankhurst, E. Sylvia., 1935 July 5.; (1 item). (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Typewritten inquiry letter from Pankhurst.
  - Pinchot, Gifford., 1929-1930.; (10 items). (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Correspondence with Pinchot over publishing dispute.
  - Sanford, John., 1937-1950.; (69 items). (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Papers documenting dispute over Sanford's The Old Man's Place.
  - Seldes, George., 1928.; (2 items). (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Handwritten letter from Seldes.
  - Seldes, Gilbert., 1916.; (4 items). (Box 4, Folder 23)
    Papers of financial agreement between Seldes and Albert Boni.
  - Shaw, George Bernard., 1917.; (2 items). (Box 4, Folder 24)
    Typewritten letter soliciting a World War I book from George Bernard Shaw
    Typed transcription of shorthand reply from George Bernard Shaw.
  - Stewart, Donald Ogden., 1947.; (1 item). (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Correspondence regarding fees for Stewart reprints.
  - Tennant, John A., 1949-1950.; (12 items). (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Letters on book purchases.
  - Unamuno, Miguel de., 1929.; (5 items). (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Correspondence with Unamuno about Three Exemplary Novels.
  - Van Doren, Mark., 1928-1933.; (54 items). (Box 4, Folder 28)
    Letters from Van Doren on World Poetry Anthology.
  - Villard, Oswald Garrison., 1931.; (9 items). (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Publishing inquiries from Villard.
  - Von Wedel, Carl., 1938.; (6 items). (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Letters and papers from Von Wedel on photography and science.
  - Wilder, Isabel., 1949-1950.; (20 items). (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Letters on international rights of her brother's work.
  - Wilder, Thornton., 1962 September 18.; (2 items). (Box 5, Folder 4)
    2 publicity photos of Wilder.
  - Wylie, Elinor., 1966.; (4 items). (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Receipts, typewritten letter, notes.
- Series 3: Contracts, 1921-1973.; (6 boxes).
  Publishing contracts for various authors and artists. Arranged alphabetically by author's surname.
  - Adams - Arens., 1924-1938.; (10 items). (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Asch - Bierce., 1925-1942.; (13 items). (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Bigelow - Bonsels., 1925-1932.; (9 items). (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Book Review Syndicate - Broun., 1925-1935.; (9 items). (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Burke - Chubb., 1924-1973.; (8 items). (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Citadel Press - Cornwall Press., 1930-1946.; (6 items). (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Courier Citizen Co. - Crowder., 1925-1938.; (7 items). (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Damon - Dial Press., 1923-1932.; (8 items). (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Diedrichs - Eastman., 1921-1940.; (6 items). (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Eddison - Ferry., 1926-1940.; (9 items). (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Field - Ford., 1924-1949.; (8 items). (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Fornaro - Handy., 1922-1949.; (11 items). (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Hapgood - Herold., 1925-1941.; (6 items). (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Hittner - Huston., 1924-1945.; (6 items). (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Inman - Kayser., 1926-1938.; (5 items). (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Kemp - Lawrence., 1926-1935.; (7 items). (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Levine - Liggett., 1926-1931.; (6 items). (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Lippmann - MacKaye., 1925-1967.; (10 items). (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Macmillan - McAdoo., 1924-1931.; (14 items). (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - McBride - Motherwell., 1924-1936.; (11 items). (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Mussey - Niles., 1922-1942.; (9 items). (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Nock - Paramount Pictures., 1926-1937.; (6 items). (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Parker - Powers Reproduction Corp., 1925-1946.; (9 items). (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Proust Publishers - Pyne., 1923-1941.; (6 items). (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Raushenbush - Rodker., 1925-1935.; (6 items). (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Rue - Rogers., 1924-1925.; (7 items). (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Sanford - Smith., 1923-1937.; (9 items). (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Snyder - Straiton., 1925-1932.; (6 items). (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Street - Symons., 1924-1931.; (5 items). (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Taggard - Tully., 1928-1933.; (8 items). (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Tully - Trotsky., 1927-1931.; (7 items). (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Unamuno - Van Doren., 1929-1946.; (6 items). (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Van Rees - Wilbur Mercantile., 1923-1933.; (8 items). (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Wilder., 1928-1959.; (7 items). (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
  - Wilder - Williams Company., 1928-1939.; (5 items). (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - W.C. Williams - Wolf., 1927-1939.; (5 items). (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Wortman - Wright., 1924-1935.; (5 items). (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Ybarra - Zweig., 1928.; (3 items). (Box 10, Folder 8)